<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Angular | AppBase]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.appbase.co/blog/categories/angular/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.appbase.co/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-14T17:00:48+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.appbase.co/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Johan Buys]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Single Page Apps]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.appbase.co/blog/2013/12/24/single-page-apps/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-24T11:16:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.appbase.co/blog/2013/12/24/single-page-apps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Single Page Apps or SPA&rsquo;s are all the rage and with good reason. About 3 years ago, I started to think about the idea and came to the conclusion that client machines have been putting on some weight in the last couple of years. We could no longer call clients &ldquo;thin&rdquo; and get away with it.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Processing power on client machines have been increasing as per <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moore's_law" target="_blank">Moore&rsquo;s law</a> and the architecture of old is not really relevant anymore.
Client machines are now powerful enough to process data and deal with logic and business rules. Processing can happen on the client without the need to send the entire viewstate to the server for each action. The latencies involved when sending a request to the server for each button press or click on a dropdown degrades the exerience because an entirely &ldquo;fresh&rdquo; page needs to be updated and sent down the wire again.</p>

<p>So that is why I decided to try and roll my own implementation, totaly oblivious to ready made frameworks available to me. My idea was to have the server deal with the data and let the client request actions via ajax calls. The main page could for arguments sake be a static html page with no server side processing what so ever.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2250/2179201684_a5fe774379.jpg" title="Spaghetti" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>My first attempts were a huge mess of spaghetti code, with all sorts of anti-patterns mixed in. Using <a href="http://www.jquery.com" target="_blank">JQuery</a> to update the DOM an do Ajax calls to the backend. As the complexity increased the readability and the maintainability decreased. Anything more than toy projects and &ldquo;hello world&rsquo;s&rdquo; would almost be impossible to fathom.</p>

<p>Then I discovered that people have been having the same problems and had created frameworks and document best practices and even coining SPA as a term. I was in awe of all the possibilities available to me, I tried a few frameworks but did not have the time nor patience to learn colplex api&rsquo;s and frameworks. So after failing to get to grips with the <a href="http://backbonejs.org" target="_blank">backbone.js</a>, syntax I discovered <a href="http://knockoutjs.com" target="_blank">Knockout.js</a> and I had nirvana, albeit only for a short while!</p>

<p>Knockout.js was great it introduced me to the wonderful world of frontend development, it helped me structure my code in controllers and views and MVVM was a great way to separate concerns and it had 2-way data binding.</p>

<p>But once again, I was stuck in a mess of spaghetti! I was starting to lose that in-love feeling, the honeymoon period was drawing to a close. I must confess: the messy code wasn&rsquo;t Knockout&rsquo;s fault it was all my own, but it seemed like a good time to reinvestigate my options.</p>

<p>So I went back and searched yet again to find something that would fit better. Then I discovered <a href="http://angularjs.org" target="_blank">AngularJs</a>. AngularJs is clean, no need to make special objects, it works with plain javascript objects, so you can use JSON sent down directly from the server. I quickly understood the basic syntax of modules, controllers and services. The inline curly braces replacing and templating is easy and intuative.</p>

<p><img src="http://angularjs.org/img/AngularJS-large.png" title="AngularJS!" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s just awesome, I now work with it on a daily basis. My code is more structured, more functional and cleaner.
By using directives I can extend HTML to define my own reusable componets and widgets. You can basically learn HTML new tricks, by adding new tags. The magic Dependency injection provides, makes it easy to use modules anywhere, the injector figures out what you want to use where and automagically adds it in. I love the use of special $scope objects to make the link between controllers and views.</p>

<p>So for me SPA development starts and ends with angular. It&rsquo;s a mature project with a clear direction and focus, it has a large and ever growing community and it&rsquo;s backed and used by Google, need I say more&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
